Howard Hunter Papers MS167
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Howard Hunter Papers
1959 -- 1996
1844 -- 1996
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Hunter, Howard
MS167
3.9 Linear Feet 5 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series: Papers; Artifacts and photographs.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of artifacts (including communion cups, plates, and drinking pitchers), correspondence, minutes, news clippings, photographs, and syllabi. Also included are Chinese Buddhist texts and a Bulletin from the Crane Theological School. The bulk of this material is dated from 1959 to 1996. Topics of this collection include the closing of the Department of Religion at Tufts University and the James A. Russell Lecture on Spiritual Life.
Biographical / Historical
Howard Hunter (1929- ) was born in Lima, Ohio. After high school in Leipsic, Ohio, he attended Ohio Northern University on a scholarship, earning a Bachelor of Science in Education in 1950. He earned a Master's degree from Ohio State in 1952. He went on to Boston University where he earned a Bachelor of Sacred Theology in 1954 and a PhD. in 1957. During this period he was also ordained a Methodist minister.
In 1957, Hunter began teaching at Tufts where he served as the Assistant Professor of Philosophy of Religion and Theology until 1961. At this time, he began working at Boston University, where he taught in the School of Theology and was the Director of Admissions until 1966. He then returned to Tufts and was appointed Chairman of the Religion Department. He retired from Tufts in 1997.
Howard's publications include the book 'Humanities, Religion and the Arts, Tomorrow' published in 1972, and 'Moral Problems in the Nurse-Patient Relationship' in 1983. Howard wrote over 30 articles and 20 reviews, and even a script for a Japanese film, The Snows of Uonoma, in 1982.
Howard traveled to many places worldwide, beginning in 1958 when he was a member of the Institute for Theological Studies at Oxford. In the 1960's he traveled around Europe and visited Israel; in 1970 he was Visiting Research Fellow in Kyoto at Doshisha University Center for the Study of Japanese Religions, and in 1976 was an invited participant at a conference at the Vatican.
Howard married Doris Leenhouts in 1957. The have one son and one daughter and three grandchildren.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Hunter, Howard; Faculty papers; Tufts University -- History; University history; Hunter, Howard; Department of Religion
- Papers, 1967 -- 1996; MS167.001; 0.75 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains original letters and correspondence about the closing of the Department of Religion at Tufts University. Newspaper clipping referring to the closing are also included in the collection. Some reference to the Russell Lecture also.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged as transferred.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - 3/14 Article Re Success pf Rel Dept., 1995; MS167.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - President DiBiaggio Letter Re: Religion Dept., 1992; MS167.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Lilly Endownment Report, 1991; MS167.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Elisabeth Ammons and Trustee List, 1994; MS167.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Why Does the Administration Refuse to Listen?, 1994 -- 1995; MS167.001.001.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1)
  - Martin Green Essay "Religion at Tufts", 1995; MS167.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Howard Hunter: Open Letter, Religion Under Fire, 1991; MS167.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - [Newspaper Clippings and Correspondence], 1990 -- 1995; MS167.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Religion Seminar- Lilly Endowment, 1987 -- 1991; MS167.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Religion Department Miscellaneous, 1967 -- 1994; MS167.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - Development Ideas, 1967 -- 1990; MS167.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - [Learning and the Ikhwan, Binder 1 of 2], 1996; MS167.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - [Orientalism and Islamic Philosophy, Binder 2 of 2], 1996; MS167.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
  - V.P. Rotberg- NEH Proposal on Expanding Religious Studies at Tufts, 1989; MS167.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
  - Copies of Letter concerning the closing of the Religion Department, 1990; MS167.001.002.00001 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
    Fall 1990
  - Articles- Religion Dept., 1990 -- 1994; MS167.001.002.00002 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
  - Recent Articles Rel. Dept S'94, 1994; MS167.001.002.00003 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
  - Annual Russell Lecture, 1983 -- 1984; MS167.001.002.00004 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
  - Russell Lecture, 1970 -- 1971; MS167.001.002.00005 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
  - Russell Lecture, 1969 -- 1970; MS167.001.002.00006 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
  - Russell Lecture, 1971 -- 1972; MS167.001.002.00007 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
  - Russell Lecture, 1972 -- 1973; MS167.001.002.00008 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
  - Russell Lecture Correspondence, 1977 -- 1978; MS167.001.002.00009 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
  - Russell Lecture Correspondence, circa 1976 -- 1977; MS167.001.002.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box MS167 Shared 1)
  - Russell Lecture Correspondence, 1975 -- 1976; MS167.001.002.00011 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
- Artifacts and Photographs, 1844 -- 1968; 1844 -- 1900; MS167.002; 3.15 Linear Feet
  This series contains a collection of artifacts that were gathered with the papers of the chairman of the Department of Religion, Howard Hunter. Many of the artifacts are from the Crane Theological School. Included in the collection are communion cups and plates and drinking pitchers. Many of the artifacts are monogrammed.
  This series is arranged by size.
  - Students Gathering, 1959; MS167.002.002.00012 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
    Arthur D. Wilmot, Moses S. Walker, Paul D. Matranga, Leo R. Dantona, Robert W. Gardner, William L. Holden, Carol R. Morris, 1959
  - Divinity Students Richard Baker and Larry Hamby washing dishes, 1959; MS167.002.002.00013 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
  - Graduating Class, 1959; MS167.002.002.00014 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
    Seated: Rolland E. Morin (with pipe), Kenneth R. Whittemore, (upper step) Charles H. Whittier. Standing L. to R. Charles W. McGenee, Loring F. Roberts, Richard F. Drinon, Alexander Meek, Jr., Dean Benjamin B. Hersey
  - Crane Alumni- Dining Room Committee, 1959; MS167.002.002.00015 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
    L-R Arthur Tripp, Arthur Webster, George Pennington, Benjamin Hersey, Howard Smith, Ernest Cassolr, Joseph Guinta, Ernest Brown
  - Unidentified Photograph, MS167.002.002.00016 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
    Removed from frame
  - Co-op of Instructors, Maseda University Tokyo, Japan, 1900 -- 1910; MS167.002.002.00017 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
  - Bulletin of Tufts University- Crane Theological School, 1967 -- 1968; MS167.002.002.00018 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
  - Chinese Buddist text in Japanese, 1875 -- 1950; MS167.002.002.00019 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
  - Primary School Reader Vol 7 in Japanese, 1894; MS167.002.002.00020 (Box MS167 Shared 1)
  - Tufts College Communion Plates, 1850 -- 1950; MS167.002.003.00001 (Box 3)
    Three Communion Plates, Two have the Tufts College monogram, and one does not.
  - Drinking Pitcher Second Universalist Church Boston, 1844; MS167.002.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Drinking Pitcher Tufts College Presented by the Students of the Divinity School, 1876-02; MS167.002.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Crane Memorial Dedication, 1900 -- 1950; MS167.002.004.00001 (Box 4)
  - Monogrammed Communion Cup, 1850 -- 1950; MS167.002.004.00002 (Box 4)
    Unidentified monogram that includes the letters S,H,I
  - Tufts College Monogrammed Communion Cup, 1850 -- 1950; MS167.002.004.00003 (Box 4)
    Two Cups monogrammed with the initials T.C.
  - Second Universalist Church Communion Cup Set of 5, 1844; MS167.002.004.00004 (Box 4)
    Set of 5 cups
  - Columbus Avenue Universalist Church Pitcher, 1880 -- 1910; MS167.002.005.00001 (Box 5)
    Presented to the Columbus Avenue Universalist Church. Rev. Dr. A.A. Miner, Pastor In memory of Mrs. Harriet A. Roberts Died Nov 25, 1885 By Mrs Mary W. Roberts